Finding Aid for Dept. of Physics (University of Michigan) records 1873-ongoing
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Physics (University of Michigan) records 1873-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.
1 oversize folders
14.5 linear feet
Correspondence and other papers dealing with departmental plans, reviews and organization, buildings and laboratories, staff recruitment, research, impact of World War I and personal affairs of various staff members especially when they were studying in Europe. Correspondence includes letters of John W. Langley, Robert A. Millikan, Harrison Randall, James M. Cork, Ernest Lawrence, Walter Stevens, John O. Reed, Henry Carhart, Karl Guthe, Fred Hodges, Horace R. Crane, and others. Also includes correspondence of chairmen Daniel Sinclair, Richard H. Sands, and Lawrence W. Jones. Efforts to locate a superconducting super collider in Michigan in the 1980s are well documented in these records.
87145 Bimu C26 2 UBImul C26
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Records were received from the Department of Physics in three accessions; the largest and most recent was in December 2001 (donor no. 1332 ).
The records are open for research.
The first course in physics at the University of Michigan, entitled "Natural Philosophy," was taught in the Fall of 1843 by George Palmer Williams, Professor of Natural Philosophy and Mathematics. A Professor of Physics and Civil Engineering, Alexander Winchell, was appointed in January 1854. The first full Professor of Physics, James Craig Watson, was named in 1860.
The department began to take shape after the Physics Building (later called the West Physics Building and now known as West Hall) was built in 1888. Prior to that, at most one professor of physics existed at a time and classes took place in the North College or University Hall. Between 1890 and 1900, several instructors, assistant professors, and junior professors were appointed to the department.
Early interest in infrared spectroscopy, led by Harrison M. Randall in 1911, brought Michigan to the forefront as a research facility in physics. In the 1950s, research into infrared spectroscopy led to discovery of the principles behind fiber optics. Beginning in 1921, R.A. Sawyer and O.S. Duffendack accomplished substantial research in visible and ultraviolet spectroscopy. In 1932 discoveries by Dennison, Uhlenbeck, Cleeton, and Williams marked the beginning of microwave spectroscopy.
From 1915 to 1925 the department realized the need for systematization and interpretation of the large numbers of experiments being done. W.F. Colby consulted with researchers and led courses in theoretical physics to fill this need, thus beginning the Theoretical Physics program. The Summer Symposia in Physics began modestly in 1923. By 1928 its focus changed to Theoretical Physics and it became national and international in scope. Lecturers included P.A.M. Dirac, Enrico Fermi, Werner Heisenberg, Wolfgang Pauli, Neils Bohr, J.R. Oppenhiemer, H.A. Bethe, and Kasimir Fajans.
Since the 1920s the Applied Physics program has worked with other departments and research units toward practical applications of physics. Examples include an alliance with industrial organizations to reduce noise in automobiles, and a partnership with the Medical School to detect infrared measurements of amino acids.
The Nuclear Physics program was developed in the 1930s, led by the interest of Michigan theorists. Harrison M. Randall consulted with other programs at the University of California and the California Institute of Technology, as well as prominent physicists such as Enrico Fermi, when forming the program. The department hosted the Summer Symposia on Nuclear Physics in 1931 and later years to build international interest. In 1936 the department built a 36-inch cyclotron with the cooperation of the Medical School and with generous support from the Rackham Trust Fund. It was used for physics experiments as well as for medical research in leukemia and polycythemia. In 1939 the cyclotron was converted to 42 inches, and in 1962 it was replaced by an 83-inch cyclotron. In the 1970s the cyclotron was phased out due to federal cuts in nuclear research funding. Michigan gained prominence in accelerator development when the world's first electron synchrotron was built by the department beginning in 1946.
After World War II, interest developed in high energy physics. The department stood strongly in the area of particle detectors, most notably in the Nobel Prize-winning development by Donald Glaser of the Bubble Chamber in the 1950s.
As the department grew, it acquired new buildings. In 1923-24, the East Physics Building (now Randall Laboratory) was built for advanced research. In 1962-63, the ten-story Physics-Astronomy Building (Now the Dennison Building) was built to house the Physics-Astronomy Library, classrooms, and laboratories.
This history was excerpted from Zorn, J., ed. On the History of Physics at Michigan. Ann Arbor: Department of Physics, 1988. The Physics Department is planning to place this publication on their website: http://www.physics.lsa.umich.edu
Chairs of the University of Michigan Department of Physics
1911-1915 Karl E. Guthe (Director of the Physical Laboratory)
1915-1941 Harrison M. Randall
1941-1955 Ernest F. Barker
1955-1965 David Dennison
1965-1972 H. Richard Crane
1972-1977 Daniel Sinclair
1977-1982 Richard H. Sands
1982-1987 Lawrence W. Jones
1987-1992 Homer A. Neal
1992-1994 John F. Ward (Interim Chair)
1994-2004 Citrad Uher
2004-present Myron Campbell
The Department of Physics records contain budget sheets, clippings, committee minutes, correspondence, departmental review reports, organizational charts, personnel records, and photographs. The records are most informative in the administrative proceedings of the department. They are least informative in curricular and research areas. The records span the years 1873-1995 and are arranged into four series: Administrative Files, Undergraduate and Graduate Programs, Research, and Awards and Special Events and L3 Project. Although there are 19th century records present, the bulk of the records cover the period from 1954 to 1991.
Subjects:
Physics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Superconducting super collider--Location--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Research.
Contributors:
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Carhart, Henry S. (Henry Smith), 1844-1920.; Cork, James M. (James Murle), 1894-; Crane, H. R. (Horace Richard), 1907-2007; Fermi, Enrico, 1901-1954.; Furstenberg, Albert Carl, 1890-1969.; Guthe, Karl Eugen, 1866-1915.; Hendel, Fred, 1916-.; Hodges, Fred Jenner, 1895-; Langley, John Williams, 1841-1918.; Lawrence, Ernest Orlando, 1901-1958.; Millikan, Robert Andrews, 1868-1953.; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967.; Randall, Harrison M. (Harrison McAllister), b. 1870.; Reed, John Oren, 1856-1916.; Reichle, Lewis.; Stevens, Walter LeConte, 1847-1927.; Uhlenbeck, George Eugène, 1900-1988.; Sinclair, Daniel.; Sands, Richard H.; Jones, Lawrence W. (Lawrence William), 1925-
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.
- Administrative Files 1873-1995
  The Administrative Files series (1873-2000, 8.8 linear feet) is divided into six subseries: Correspondence, Committees, Facilities and Equipment, Finances, Personnel, Reports and Topical Files.
  - Correspondence 1889-1932, 1964-1991
    The Correspondence subseries (1889-1932, 1964-1991, 2 linear feet) contains Departmental Correspondence, 1889-1932; and Chairman's Correspondence, 1964-1991. The early departmental correspondence includes letters of John W. Langley, Robert A. Millikan, Harrison M. Randall, James M. Cork, Ernest Lawrence, Walter Stevens, John O. Reed, Henry Carhart, Karl Guthe, H. R. Crane, and others. Correspondence from 1917 and 1918 documents World War I submarine detection research done under Harrison M. Randall. The Chairman's Correspondence is dominated by the papers of Lawrence W. Jones, chairman from 1982 to 1987, and covers the daily affairs of the department. The Jones correspondence also includes material predating his tenure as chairman.
    - Departmental Correspondence 1889-1932
      - Undated, Circa 1889-1932 (Box 1)
      - 1889-1898 (Box 1)
      - 1899-1908 (Box 1)
      - 1909-1916 (Box 1)
      - 1917 (Box 1)
      - January 1918 (Box 1)
      - February-April 1918 (Box 1)
      - May-September 1918 (Box 1)
      - October-December 1918 (Box 1)
      - 1919-1932 (Box 1)
    - Chairmen's Correspondence 1964-1991
      - Daniel Sinclair September 1974-August 1976 (Box 1)
      - Richard H. Sands July 1977-April 1982 (Box 1)
      - Lawrence W. Jones
        - College of LS&A January 1984-May 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Vice President for Research May 1982-February 1986 (Box 1)
        - Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost January 1982-February 1986 (Box 1)
        - President Harold Shapiro May 1983-February 1984 (Box 1)
        - October 1964-December 1973 (Box 1)
        - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
        - June 1976-May 1981 (Box 1)
        - January 1982-January 1983 (Box 1)
        - February 1983-April 1983 (Box 1)
        - May 1983-June 1983 (Box 1)
        - July 1983 (Box 1)
        - August 1983-September 1983 (Box 1)
        - October 1983-December 1983 (Box 1)
        - January 1984-April 1984 (Box 1)
        - May 1984-June 1984 (Box 2)
        - July 1984-September 1984 (Box 2)
        - October 1984-November 1984 (Box 2)
        - December 1984-January 1985 (Box 2)
        - February 1985-April 1985 (Box 2)
        - May 1985-June 1985 (Box 2)
        - July 1985-September 1985 (Box 2)
        - October 1985 (Box 2)
        - November 1985-December 1985 (Box 2)
        - January 1986-February 1986 (Box 2)
        - March 1986-May 1986 (Box 2)
        - June 1986-August 1986 (Box 2)
        - September 1986-October 1986 (Box 2)
        - November 1986-December 1986 (Box 2)
        - January 1987-February 1987 (Box 2)
        - March 1987-June 1987 (Box 2)
      - Homer A. Neal
        - September 1987-January 1991 (Box 2)
  - Committees 1954-2001
    The Committees subseries (1954-2000, 1.35 linear feet) documents committees cutting across areas of the department, such as the Executive Committee and various departmental review committees. The 2006 addition to the collection included one linear foot of Executive Committee materials dating from 1973 to 2000. The material is arranged by date and includes meeting action items, minutes and related documentation.
    - Ad Hoc Group on Minority Graduate Students in Natural Science 1984 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Joint Physics-Engineering Programs 1984 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee
      - Agendas April 1981-October 1990 (Box 3)
      - Agenda, Action Items and Related Documents
        - 1988 (Box 11)
        - September 1989-December 1991 (Box 11)
        - January-December 1992 (Box 11)
        - January-June, 1993 (Box 11)
        - July 1993-August 1994 (Box 11)
        - September-December 1994 (Box 11)
        - January-May 1995 (Box 11)
        - June-December 1995 (Box 11)
        - January-December 1996 (Box 11)
        - January-December 1997 (Box 11)
        - January-December 1998 (Box 11)
        - January-May 1999 (Box 11)
        - January-April 2000 (Box 11)
      - Minutes October 1954-1978 (Box 3)
        - October 1954-July 1966, 3 folders
        - 1973-1978 (Box 11)
      - Correspondence June 1979-July 1987 (Box 3)
      - Elections 1989-1993 (Box 11)
    - External Advisory Committee 1971, 1982, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Internal Review Committee 1974-1975, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - LS&A Technical Services Review Committee, Survey and Recommendations 1985, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Physics Faculty Meetings September 1982-October 1990 (Box 3)
    - Public Relations Committee September 1986 (Box 3)
    - Target-of-Opportunity Committee 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Visiting Committee 1988-1991 (Box 3)
  - Facilities and Equipment 1886-1919, 1953-1991
    The Facilities and Equipment subseries (1886-1919, 1953-1992, 2.8 linear feet) contains files on departmental equipment, shops, and buildings. Of note are the space planning files, which document the move to the Dennison Building and the Randall Bridge Proposal; and the department's efforts to build a Superconducting Super Collider near Ann Arbor. For cyclotron files, see the Research series. The 2006 accession added two linear feet to this subseries. The documentation is mainly additional Superconducting Super Collider reports for the Dundee and Stockbridge, Michigan sites.
    - Bendix Vacuum Tank December 1984-February 1985 (Box 3)
    - Computers 1979-1991
      - Acquisition Correspondence 1982-1991 (Box 3)
      - Department Computer Committee 1991 (Box 3)
      - CAEN/MacIntosh Instrument Shop (Box 3)
      - ISAAC 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - PINET 1990 (Box 3)
      - Proposed Center for Scientific Computation 1983-1984 (Box 3)
      - Vax Cluster Departmental Computer System 1979-1991 (Box 3)
    - Molecular Beam Epitaxy System March 1983-November 1984 (Box 3)
    - Paper Recycling Program October 1990-November 1990 (Box 3)
    - Physics Instrument Shop 1953-1967, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Shops and Laboratories, Correspondence 1963, 1976, 1985, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Space Planning 1886-1919, 1956-1990
      - Early Reports 1886-1919
        - "Why a Physical Lab is Needed," Henry S. Carhart, circa 1886-1909 (Box 3)
        - "Report of Committee on the Establishment of a New Central Shop for Furnishing Mechanical Service to All Departments," 1919 (Box 3)
      - Departmental Correspondence and Reports 1964, 1972-1990 (Box 3)
      - LS&A Correspondence January 1983-May 1987 (Box 3)
      - Dennison Building (Formerly Physics and Astronomy Building)
        - Architect's Presentation Drawing (Folder UBImul C26)
        - Conference Notes March 1960-January 1962 (Box 3)
        - Construction, Correspondence and Photos 1958-1963 (Box 3)
      - Randall Lab
        - Floor Plan Drawings (8 sheets), circa 1924 (Folder UBImul C26)
        - Randall Lab Addition November 1956, December 1957 (Box 3)
        - Randall Bridge Proposal and Correspondence 1980-1988 (Box 3)
        - Renovation and Construction Projects Committee 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Superconducting Super Collider 1983-1986
      - Clippings 1984-1985 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence and Reports
        - July 1983-December 1984 (Box 4)
        - February 1985-September 1985 (Box 4)
        - November 1985-October 1986 (Box 4)
        - Undated (Box 4)
      - Meetings and Workshops
        - Workshop on Accelerator Physics Issues for a Superconducting Super Collider December 12-17, 1983 (Box 4)
        - Meeting Proceedings June 1984-November 1984 (Box 4)
        - Workshop on Reliability in Accelerator Operations December 6, 1984 (Box 4)
        - Ann Arbor Seminar January 7, 1985 (Box 4)
        - Tri-State Superconducting Super Collider Meeting January 31, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Equipment Correspondence May 1963-June 1990 (Box 4)
    - Prospectus for New Physics Building and Renovation of the Randall Laboratory Building September 1988 (Box 12)
    - Superconducting Super Collider (SSC)
      - Final Environmental Impact Statement, vol. I-III December 1988, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Siting the Superconducting Super Collider in Michigan--Dundee Site, vol. I-VIII, appendices and map supplement 1987, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Siting the Superconducting Super Collider in Michigan--Stockbridge Site, vol. I-III 1987 (Box 12)
      - Siting the Superconducting Super Collider in Michigan--Stockbridge Site, vol. IV-VIII, appendices and map Supplement 1987, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Superconducting Super Collider Laboratory September 1989 (Box 13)
      - Superconducting Super Collider, Monthly Progress Report June-August 1992 (Box 13)
  - Finances 1873-1947, 1964-1995
    The Finances subseries (1873-1947, 1964-1995, .2 linear feet) is divided into three categories: Budget, Funding, and Salaries. The Budget material contains early requests for appropriations for the department. The Funding material documents the department's efforts to gain funding for individuals and projects. Salaries contains salary comparisons and negotiations.
    - Budget 1873-1875, 1912-1947
      - Requests for Appropriations for the Physics Department by Professor Merriman March 1873, June 1873 (Box 4)
      - Request for Appropriations for Apparatus for the Physics Department by Professor Langley October 1875 (Box 4)
      - "Requests from the Physics Department as Affecting the Budget for 1916-1917" (Box 4)
      - Budget Sheets 1912-1947 (Box 6)
    - Funding 1977-1995
      - Corporate October 1978-November 1989 (Box 4)
      - Graduate Student Aid May 1973-April 1982 (Box 4)
      - Private Endowments 1986-1995 (Box 4)
      - University of Michigan
        - Vice President for Research 1977, 1983-1990 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous 1981-1990 (Box 4)
      - United States Government
        - Department of Education Proposal October 1990 (Box 4)
        - National Science Foundation June 1987-October 1990 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous 1986-1990 (Box 4)
    - Salaries 1964-1991
      - Correspondence 1967-1991 (Box 4)
      - Change from Two-to Three-Month Summer 1964-1968 (Box 4)
      - Comparisons with Other Physics Departments 1966-1986 (Box 4)
  - Personnel 1962-1991
    The Personnel subseries (1962-1991, .5 linear feet) documents the organization of the department and the faculty search process. Organizational charts, hiring policies, search committees, position requests, position descriptions, position inquiries, and recruitment files are included in this subseries.
    - Organizational Charts and Staff Distribution 1962, 1965, 1979-1985, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Office Responsibilities and Staffing 1978-1991 (Box 4)
    - Policies and Search Committees 1971-1986 (Box 4)
    - Position Requests and Descriptions 1979-1991 (Box 4)
    - Position Inquiries 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Review of the Need for Astrophysics Appointments 1986-1986 (Box 4)
    - Condensed Matter Applicants February 1988 (Box 4)
    - Post-Doctoral Inquiries 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Recruitment Files
      - Ball, James S. 1963 (Box 4)
      - Warner, Robert 1963 (Box 4)
      - Hofstadter, Robert 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Reports 1974-1991
    The Reports subseries (1974-1991, .2 linear feet) contains historical, evaluative, planning, policy and summary reports about the department.
    - Annual Overview of Physics Department 1991 (Box 4)
    - Departmental Ranking (National) 1982 (Box 4)
    - Emeritus Faculty Activity Report September 1990 (Box 4)
    - Five-Year Plan for Physics 1978-1980, 1985 (Box 4)
    - "Questions on Race and Diversity Issues," December 1990 (Box 4)
    - Memorial Statements: Henry S. Carhart, David M. Dennison, Otto Laporte, George A. Lindsay (Box 4)
    - "On the History of Physics at Michigan: Nuclear Physics," 1986 (Box 4)
    - Press Release 1985 (Box 4)
    - "Research in the Department of Physics," circaFebruary 1985 (Box 4)
    - "Overview and Long-Range Plan," 1990 (Box 4)
    - "The Physics Development Initiative Provost Review," 1991 (Box 4)
    - "Program Evaluation Report on the Department of Physics," 1974 (Box 4)
    - Selected Features of the History of the University with Especial Reference to the Department of Physics, Ann Arbor, MI April 20, 1937 (Box 6)
    - State of the Department 1987, 1956-1991 (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    - 1920-1992
      - Budget Files circa 1920-1945, 1 microfilms (Box 14)
      - Clippings (Box 14)
      - Correspondence
        - Chairman (David Dennison) 1955-1959 (Box 14)
        - Correspondence on Teaching Loads 1966-1974 (Box 14)
      - College of Literature, Science and the Arts
        - Curriculum Committee 1989-1995 (Box 14)
        - Faculty Meetings 1992-1993 (Box 14)
      - Committees
        - Astrophysics Institute 1991-1992 (Box 14)
        - External Advisory October 8-9, 1990 (Box 14)
        - Physics Advisory Council May 11-12, 1989 (Box 14)
      - Departmental History Files
        - David Dennison circa 1976 (Box 14)
        - Harrison Randall circa 1969 (Box 14)
        - George Palmer Williams circa 1988 (Box 14)
      - Development--Donor Prospect List March 31, 1989 (Box 14)
      - External Review 1988-1989 (Box 14)
      - Faculty Bibliography 1894-1981 (index cards in two steel boxes--located in Box 13) (Box 14)
      - Faculty Luncheons 1990-1993 (Box 14)
      - Meetings with Dean Goldberg circa 1991 (Box 14)
      - Paper, "A Tribute to William L. Williams," April 21, 1988 (Box 14)
      - Personnel
        - Administrative Reorganization 1992-1993 (Box 14)
        - Teaching Assignments 1981-1986 (Box 14)
      - Projects (Box 15)
        - Granite Project 1989 (Box 15)
        - Harrison Randall Laboratory Addition "Groundbreaking Ceremony," 1993 (Box 15)
      - Proceedings of the Alfred Hill Memorial Symposium March 30, 1989 (Box 15)
      - Proposal
        - A Proposal to the Department of Education for the Graduate Assistance in Areas of National Need Grant to Create a Program of Doctoral Study Optimization Fellowships in Physics October 19, 1990 (Box 15)
      - Reports
        - Development Agenda and Department Overview June 28, 1991 (Box 15)
        - Faculty Research Activities
          - May 17, 1991 (Box 15)
          - Fall 1992 (Box 15)
          - Fall 1993 (Box 15)
        - Long Range Plan 1990-1993 (Box 15)
        - Long Range Plan 2000-2004 and Beyond, December 2000 (Box 15)
        - Michigan Institute for Astrophysics July 21, 1993 (Box 15)
        - Overview and Long Range Plan October 29, 1990 (Box 15)
        - Overview and Long Range Plan January 7, 1991 (Box 15)
        - Physics at Michigan undated (Box 15)
        - State of the UM Physics Department September 15, 1993 (Box 15)
      - Salaries 1952-1965 (Box 15)
      - Survey of the Midwest Departments of Physics May 1982 (Box 15)
      - Symposium--Group Theory and Special Symmetrics in Nuclear Physics September 1991 (Box 15)
      - Undergraduate and Graduate Programs
        - Applied Physics Program circa 1987 (Box 15)
        - Authorized Strength Reports circa 1981-1988 (Box 15)
        - Discussions with the Literature, Science & Arts Executive Committee on the Future Development of the Department of Physics 1991 (Box 15)
        - Graduate Programs History circa 1975-1983 (Box 15)
        - W.K. Kellogg Foundation--Center for Educational Improvement through Collaboration (CEIC) circa 1989 (Box 15)
- Undergraduate and Graduate Programs 1956-1991
  The Undergraduate and Graduate Programs series (1956-1991, .25 linear feet) is divided into three subseries: Committees, 1960-1991, Curriculum, 1956-1991, and Students, 1974-1991.
  - Committees 1960-1991
    The Committees subseries (1960-1991) contains correspondence, minutes, and reports from committees having to do with curriculum and/or students.
    - Applied Physics Executive Committee 1984, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - Curriculum Committee Minutes September 1972-March 1977 (Box 5)
    - Faculty-Student Curriculum Study Committee Report, After 1969 (Box 5)
    - Ph.D. Qualifying Committee, Circa May 1960 (Box 5)
    - Undergraduate Affairs Committee Report on Introductory Laboratories, Circa January 1991 (Box 5)
    - Committee on the Undergraduate Physics Experience, Charge 1990 (Box 5)
  - Curriculum 1956-1991
    The Curriculum, subseries (1956-1991) consists of correspondence, enrollment reports, and information about the Graduate and Honors Programs.
    - Correspondence September 1972-March 1991 (Box 5)
    - B.A. in Physics Planning January 1991 (Box 5)
    - Class and Section Enrollment Reports, Fall 1956-Spring 1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Graduate Program Information 1966-1979, 1989 (Box 5)